hey folks welcome to the 13th Dark Horse
podcast livestream I am here with dr.
Heather hi as always and we are ready to
chat about some very interesting topics
this week do we have any business that
needs to be covered up front not that I
remember right now yes I don't I don't
recall any business either we were
slightly thrown we are seeing a
brand-new kind of error on our live
stream where are apparently happening
and we cannot see them for some reason
no matter how we link up to the channel
but for the moment it doesn't seem to be
interfering with our ability to
broadcast so we're going to go as usual
and hope that that clears up as normal
alright so where shall we start why
don't you start with what you had in
mind all right let us talk about the
fact that for many weeks in fact since
the beginning of this crisis the
question of herd immunity has been
central to many people's thinking and
I'm watching something unfold over
social media where the consensus around
the accessibility of herd immunity as a
solution to the kovat 19:00 crisis seems
to be evaporating and I think it's about
time that it did so just say that again
what is evaporating the consensus that
herd immunity is actually the the road
out of this crisis for us is evaporating
and I think it's evaporating around
several different concepts one the
information that once sick with SARS
Cove - one is immune going forward has
not emerged it's still probable that
that is the case but we really don't
know that it is the case and therefore
gambling on herd immunity is a mistake
because it's quite possible that people
who had this virus are going to be
vulnerable in the future and therefore
herd immunity is not even a thing of
course without the ability to time
travel this always would have been
impossible to know at this point right
that there's just no way to know whether
those who have been exposed and have
antibodies now will in a year six months
six years any of those things yeah so
there's that and then I think there's a
conflation that in fact herd immunity is
desirable if it is achieved through
vaccine and in fact that's basically
what a vaccine does it creates a kind of
herd immunity without illness so anyway
people have been thinking about this
emerging naturally and in fact in places
like Britain they have experimented with
it at the level of policy but I think
and they and I think effectively that
was what was being experimented with in
Sweden as well which as we talked about
a couple of livestreams ago the numbers
and Sweden versus their close neighbors
were are quite a bit higher or something
like six to nine times higher per capita
I believe was the analysis that I had
done than in neighboring Norway I think
it was right so in any case it's
interesting that the the collective
wisdom around where we are and what the
road out looks like is changing but at
the same time we're watching a kind of
obvious fragmentation of our collective
will to fight this together I mean we
have two factions we have a bunch of
people pushing the idea that it is time
to open things back up because well I
think they would most specifically name
the economic concerns but they appear
those who are pushing the open it back
up now narrative appear to have no
awareness about how much danger we are
in and how many unknowns remain it's
really easy to want simple binary
solutions right and this is we've raised
this before a number of times but it's
it's in some ways a strange it might
appear to be a strange position for us
to be in as people who have talked about
the binary or strongly by
nature of the sex and gender
respectively but in general in complex
systems you don't have clear binaries
with clear boundaries between the
categories and certainly you know many
weeks ago and with growing loudness now
there are calls to just open it up
already
and just tell us what the predictions
are just tell us what's gonna happen
well we don't know what's going to
happen this is exactly the point this is
this is a a cat a new cat to the show
actually I think this is one of the
others this virus has no history with
humans before six or eight months ago
and so we do not know how it is going to
continue to change and in fact that's
one of the things we'll be talking about
here today yeah so we have to I think we
have to separate between two things I
think we have to separate between the
binary maybe it's three things the
binary the bimodal and the complex that
nets to some sort of a binary choice so
the problem is we do have a binary
choice in some sense between two kinds
of policy there's one kind of policy
that airs in the direction of caution of
medical caution epidemiological caution
on the basis of what we do not yet know
and the hazards that might lurk and then
there is another policy approach which
basically says well there is a cost to
remaining on lockdown in socially
distanced and there is a cost to opening
back up and we think we know that it is
certainly better for everyone if we just
open it back up and there's a naive
version of that which is this isn't so
bad
and there is a sophisticated version
which sounds more like you know a lot of
people are going to die from the
depression that's coming to and we have
to compare these two but the real
question I think is how I don't think
our discussion is an
good our collective discussion is any
good yet there's there are points here
which I know we need to be talking about
that we are not talking about I have yet
to hear them anywhere and I know that a
rich discussion that is a non polarized
discussion a discussion in which we all
arrived with the intent to figure out
what is best for us and us could mean
Americans better if it means citizens of
the world but we could be having an
important dialogue but the problem is
this tendency for things to become
political which we've talked about
before is making it impossible to have
the proper discussion about well what do
we actually know about where we are and
what does it imply so one of the
questions that I keep waiting to hear
emerge I hope it catches on from here I
guess is if you open things back up you
will create more infection unless you're
one of these people who believes that
this is not a real thing those people
are crazy as far as I can tell but but
just to be clear the this isn't even a
real thing faction is different from
yeah it's real but I don't know where it
came from or I think it came from this
or you know there are a number of
hypotheses over in the mainstream
narrative looks like a cover story or is
at least covering the fact that we don't
really know and there's a whole lot of
possible hypothesis space and there
which we've talked about a number of
times here but at the far end of
possibility space is this isn't even
real have you even met anyone who has
come down with 19 right and you know
let's put it this way I think we always
have to leave a category for what I
would call the UH thunk that is some way
that things could be unfolding as we see
them through some mechanism we haven't
yet entertained but but that's not a
very high probability we have a corona
virus circulating it seems to be causing
a disease we call Cove it 19 it seems to
have emerged from wuhan through whatever
mechanism
and it's causing a pandemic that
involves an awful lot of people having
blood clots strokes heart attacks lungs
filling with goo all sorts of these
pathologies we've discussed but alright
let's get back to the question there is
a virus that appears to be new to this
human population that means it is
inherently experimenting with mechanisms
to transmit itself from one person to
the next
it is experimenting as we've talked
about on this podcast before what all
evolved creatures are trying to do is
lodge themselves as far into the future
as they can basically we're all trying
not to go extinct and so the farther you
can launch yourself in the future the
better off you are so can I say like I
like the language that we've used before
a little bit better that it is exploring
space it is exploring possibility space
as opposed to it is experimenting just
because experiment you know for those
people who are listening and not
watching and can't see your square
Coates square quick scare quotes around
experimenting this is not we're not
talking about human experimentation on
the coronavirus which very may very well
may have happened we're talking about
the virus itself basically exploring
space into which it can successfully
move and thrive yeah when I say
experiment I mean it in the same way
that we would say natural experiment you
know who I is a natural experiment in
invasive species right nobody set it up
that way it just it allows us to test
hypotheses by looking at the pattern so
the whatever our language choice is
there's a question about how effective
this virus is going to be in moving into
the future we humanity are presumably
all United it with the intent to give it
as little room to get into the future as
possible we would like to end its
interaction with humans as quickly as
possible one of the factor
that dictates how successful we are
likely to be is how much area how much
area in design space it has to explore
new combinations of things and to the
extent that we are divided over the
question about whether it's time to open
back up the group that is pushing a
quick return to normalcy is effectively
gambling on all of our behalf on the
extra space that the virus will now have
to discover ways of persisting in the
human population
so we talked in an early livestream
about one very bad possibility here is
that this virus becomes a fellow
traveler with humans indefinitely like
another flu now if it became less
dangerous and then it currently is then
it currently is and became persistent
that would be a devastating blow it
would not be a fatal blow to humanity
but it would be a huge setback and you
would have to put the losses that would
come from having a second flu-like
phenomenon circulating in humans
you would have to stack them against the
cost of remaining in lockdown now and
the problem is those costs are
effectively indefinitely large because
the future is indefinitely long and if
it becomes a permanent feature then
those costs will simply mount every year
yes they will become normalized right so
we have to think in terms of what is our
best chance of taking this thing that
has now spread far and wide and
preventing it from spreading further
keeping it in as few bodies as possible
so it has as little room to discover new
ways of infecting us as we can manage is
in the long term surely right so in any
case have you heard anybody else say
that that we're trying to reduce the
amount of evolutionary space it has to
discover
I don't I don't think so but you know we
we spend a lot of time talking so I've
certainly I've heard that my own house
yes but how do we lodge this in the
public discussion so that people when
somebody suggests hey it's time to open
it back up
you know crashing an economy is nothing
that you have a right to do yes there
are gonna be desk but they're always
desk these arguments that we constantly
hear in favor of opening it back up
ignore the harm we are doing to
ourselves in the distant future if we
give it too much room now wellness I
mean this is always the case with with
with policy that it values the short
term over the long term and it is always
true that those things that are
evolutionary successful are successful
because they have managed to yes survive
the short term but to launch themselves
into the future you know in the past
they launch themselves into the future
and there are very very many strategies
and lineages that fail to do that which
we now have you know either fossil or
much more likely no evidence at all they
ever existed so I think I think it'll be
very hard to successfully lodge a
popular argument and I don't mean that
popular is compared to unpopular but an
argument that gets good traction in in
mainstream space that sounds like we
need to block access to X nu
explorations nixed mmm niche exploration
space for the virus that's just that's
not going to play but talking again I
would say you know you you would you
would begun to talk about the
distinction between binary and bimodal
and complexity space and I think you
know might if we're going to do that it
might be worth actually defining our
Terms sure but it is also true that lock
down versus no lock down is a false
choice but this is a dichotomy that no
one should be actually finding
themselves on and it is you know as as I
said a few livestreams ago I feel like
we are in this SUSE and landscape of
star bellied stages and stages without
where people have begun to label the
selves you know the the maggot from the
2016 election was an obvious label it
was an obviously obvious star in your
belly to identify you know I like you I
don't like you or vice versa or whatever
it was right
and now masks in stores where they're
not mandated by the stores is becoming
that and that is freaking dangerous so
using external markers of tribal
affiliation is both a very human and
very dangerous and we can be better than
that and also we need a more nuanced
discussion of what easing restrictions
while still remaining cognizant of the
hazards might look like so the idea that
masks is succumbing to fear wearing
masks succumbing to fear and and
trusting the mainstream media that's
that batshit crazy right that doesn't
make any sense at all
but it's hard to lodge that in the
current environment how about we can
begin to allow people to you know in
places like Michigan to actually shop
for seeds and to you know do things that
are actually going to help them you know
help help some of the economy come back
alive and help them keep their mental
health and actually move forward into
the world
into the future as complete humans as
opposed to shells of humans as opposed
to treating this like a you're basically
everyone's in quarantine versus no one's
in quarantine at all those those don't
make sense as alternative choices so
part of the problem is that we function
at many levels some of them official and
some of them not official as a
representative democracy we are supposed
to be represented in our epidemiological
interests by a scientific community who
is supposed to speak for us and
unfortunately we are now seeing on many
different fronts these communities
corrupted
by obvious economic influences we see
them frankly covering their own asses
and therefore not able to tell us what
we need to know and increasingly I mean
especially I you know do not have a deep
connection to the virality community I'm
really mostly becoming aware of who the
big players are in this group but I'm
finding almost nobody who is still
officially sanctioned by the major
institutions who is not telling what
appeared to me to be obvious fictions
about where we are and it's not to say
that most of what they say isn't true
but it's to say I have a very hard time
taking them seriously when they're
telling me things that if I go put on my
biologist hat and I go research on my
own turn out not to be right so I'm sure
I mean I think I have some sense of what
kinds of things you're talking about but
I'm sure that people will want to know
what specifically referring to but this
seems a decent place to segue into just
a comparison and this isn't biologists
but Zack if you want to put this up on
April 30th the intelligence community
for the United States put out a
statement on the origins of Cove at 19
and its first short and it reads as
follows oh well the Office of the
Director of National Intelligence today
issued the following intelligence
community statement quote the entire
intelligence community has been
consistently providing critical support
to US policy makers and those responding
to the coab in 19 virus which originated
in China the intelligence community also
concurs with the wide scientific
consensus the Kovach 19 virus was not
man-made or genetically modified as we
do in all crises the community's experts
respond by surging resources and
producing critical intelligence on
issues vital to u.s. national security
the IC will continue to rigorously
examine emerging information and
intelligence to determine whether the
outbreak began through contact with
infected animals or if it was the result
of an accident at a laboratory in a
Wuhan so they are saying consensus they
agree with that what they've used the
scientific consensus that it was not
man-made or genetically modified and
then they say but we
we'll continue to take in new
information which is admirable and
frankly completely necessary to
investigate whether it's infected
animals or might be the result of an
accident at a lab in Wuhan that was on
April 30th at the same moment I'll then
take the screen down for a second sack
while they find this at the same moment
science magazine was reporting that okay
you could put it back up the NIH which
is the National Institute of Health the
major player and funding of medical
research in the United States along with
the NSF NIH is axing about coronavirus
grant a quote horrible precedent and
might break rules
critics say so same day as the
intelligence report comes out there is a
report in one of the two biggest
scientific journals in the world that is
it's a journalistic report reporting on
the fact that one of the giant NIH
grants which has been extent for six
years already and which supported
collaborative research between the US
and China and that coronaviruses has
been pulled it's not clear from this
article whether or not that's a legit
move I don't think legal is an
appropriate terminology here because
these are it's a federal granting agency
but you know presumably has some law
oversight but probably there's language
in it that allows them to withdraw at
any moment right
but cert seems to be unprecedented and
certainly breaks at least some rules of
their own internal language and the
expectations that people who get grants
pis and their their associates certainly
never expect to have their money pulled
mid grant stream you know all grants
have some amount of tenure two of them
so amount of time during which they
progress and many grants are expected to
be able to continue for further rounds
if they apply for them and have made
appropriate progress in the interim and
I don't know any of the details of this
particular grant
but how interesting really that within
the US on the same day the intelligence
community of this official position is
this is fine you know this there's
there's nothing to see here folks
there's nothing there's no man behind
the curtain in fact don't even look at
him
don't even ask if there is one that NIH
pulls funding for a long-standing effort
to study coronaviruses in bats that is a
collaborative effort between the US and
China yeah so you can see that that
juxtaposition makes no sense from the
outside exactly there's nothing about
this that requires detailed scientific
knowledge this the intelligence
community is saying one thing with
absolute clarity and we are behaving
very differently at the level of what
kind of work we are funding at the same
time but even more disturbing I think is
the fact that the virology community
that is the sanctioned tenured research
one University virology community is
monolithic in its embrace of the idea
that this is an unmodified virus that
came from nature while people who are
not part of that community but are
expert enough to navigate much of the
data that is available to us in the
public are reaching very different
conclusions now I want to be super
careful here a as we've said before we
are not going to advance conspiracy
theories we will advance conspiracy
hypotheses because that is the nature of
these things I thought in by advance
also we probably don't want to get into
the business of dissecting every single
word that we choose to use but by
advance you mean discuss and as evidence
mounts for any above others we will
speak about those that seem to be less
supported less often and those that seem
to be more supported more often while
still maintaining that they are in fact
hypotheses for which evidence could come
forward that would falsify them and this
dropped them off the list of plausible
explanations and you know for those of
you who are new to the game of theory
you should understand theorists do not
generate theories you cannot you can
generate hypotheses and at the point
that they
become supported so that they are the
assumption that they is that they are
true like the earth goes around the Sun
or that you know the information that
allows heredity in morphology comes
through DNA these things then become
theories at the point that they are
they're not immune to being falsified
but they become the default assumption
so we will offer hypotheses we will
advance them in the sense of putting
them on the table it doesn't mean that
we backed them I have to say I am still
rooting for the idea that somehow this
is a natural virus that escaped without
the scientific community's involvement
as a scientist I want that to be the
case but I have to say the evidence that
that's what happened is amazingly weak
the narrative is very strong but this is
such a critical distinction and it you
know it gets at the naturalistic fallacy
the idea that what is is not what ought
to be that good scientists good everyone
who are trying to understand things in a
scientific way may well come to believe
that something is true while
simultaneously wishing fervently that it
were not true these we often find
ourselves in this position it is indeed
exactly why we argue actually an
evolutionary perspective on humanity and
on the entire world is exactly the thing
that you need in order to change those
things that evolution has handed us
which are not beautiful or wonderful for
us so what are we to make of the fact of
those who are in the best position to
advance our interests and the best
position to understand what is taking
place appear to be monolithically
subscribed to a narrative that does not
stand up to scrutiny in other words it
may be that many of those people believe
this is a natural virus but their
certainty that that's the only way this
could have gotten into humans in wuhan
is simply unjustified by anything I've
seen anywhere yeah well the NIH just
pulled a grant
doctor was at Kyle siddell who we talked
about in an earlier livestream lost his
position at the hospital where he was
working for the crime of going on
YouTube and talking about his suspicions
that the treatment with ventilators was
not the best treatment for patients the
video by the current County doctors
which I basically eviscerated a couple
of live streams ago I don't think they
were right I don't think that their
analysis was good faith but they
absolutely need to be able to have voice
that was pulled down from YouTube there
are there are a number of frankly crazy
conspiracy theories going around that
keep on getting pulled so there seems to
be widespread effort by the sensors
which are in the case of NIH federal
sensors in the case of YouTube private
corporation sensors to keep us keep us
on the straight and narrow you know keep
us on a particular narrative so who wins
by us all talking about and coming to
think that we're sophisticated for not
paying any attention to the other
hypotheses who wins by by having the
space of possible explanations winnow to
a single one which frankly for those of
us who are trying to understand what's
going on that single explanation is
looking less and less likely to be true
and yeah I just turned the question
around on you at some level but I also
just I was trying to outline all the
places we've seen all the mechanisms by
which we seem to be seeing dissenting
voices silence so at one level sorry
before I turn that back over to you at
one level this simply could be it's that
kind of coercion that people can look
around and say oh I see what happens to
those who ask the questions or who or
who ruminate online about things that
aren't within the narrative that has
been accepted it's not worth it to me
I either you know either feel like
actually I'm doing important work here
I'm a health care worker who need
you can keep on doing the work ideas so
I'm gonna keep my thoughts to myself or
I'm a virologist with wait a tenure or
not even tenure yet and I can't afford
to lose my position so you know it's
it's really easy to imagine that this is
about courage or not but of course it's
not that simple well it's not that
simple I think most people just simply
don't understand we all know on ebay for
example there is a perverse incentive
towards positive reviews so if somebody
you know has 95 percent positive reviews
on ebay you know something's probably
wrong because that's pretty low so we
have similar networks inside of academia
and it is not obvious from the outside
but the degree to which a virologist who
was not absolutely on message well what
I was going to say was top-tier in terms
of their security would be very
vulnerable for stepping out of line if
the perception of the community is our
well-being into the future depends on
the story not being we screwed up and we
created one of the largest historical
errors ever all right if this is a you
know it would be an error presumably our
most likely it would be an error on some
given day where some person slipped up
in some procedure and this thing escaped
into the world but now we're dealing
with a global pandemic we're dealing
with the likelihood of hundreds of
thousands or maybe eventually millions
of deaths this is a major error right
if the virality community is in some way
responsible for it then we don't know
what virology will look like going
forward and that's a very strong
incentive for people frankly to convince
themselves that the official explanation
the nature cat or whatever it is is the
story and that everybody else is a
conspiracy theorist so we get to Bob
rivers concept of self-deception being
much more powerful than simple deception
it's far easier to lie successfully if
you have first lied to yourself about
what it is that you believe right so as
a countermeasure what I would suggest
and if I can actually just go back to
something you said that I think we need
to emphasize there is a lot of
conspiracy stuff circulating around
kovat 19 most of it is garbage
some of it is partially garbage and
these are the toughest ones to deal with
or the partial garbage the partial
garbage ones where my hypothesis is
offered it may contain a degree of the
truth or it may contain the truth but it
is coupled with things that are
absolutely untrue it may match your
priors and some regards and you think oh
yeah right then they say something that
you know it's wrong I think well how do
I match these things up because there's
a whole lot that I can't assess on my
own from first principles I know some of
these things are true and and other
people aren't talking about them I know
this isn't so how is it that you
separate the wheat from the chaff right
and in general for me as somebody who
finds I must go look at these if I'm
being told that this couldn't possibly
have emerged from the do you know how
many labs there are in wuhan that study
coronaviruses from bats one - oh yeah I
know I find that kind of shocking one of
them is actually a couple hundred meters
from the fish market I mean it's how is
that not a famous fact maybe I've been
lied to maybe that's not even true but I
certainly read an analysis that provided
a map that showed this right we've all
got a friendly neighborhood for allergy
lab just down the street well that's the
other thing and in fact one of the
better analyses that I've seen started
with the question of okay yes it is
surprising that that there is a virology
lab in Wuhan that studies coronaviruses
from bats and that this epidemic started
there but the first question was well
maybe these things are all over the
place and so that's not that surprising
right they're not all over the place
okay there are two Biggie's right well
in the US but I just asked
that maybe these things are all over the
place and therefore that's not so
surprising this is so important this
this is the step that is often missing
when people start promoting conspiracy
hypotheses as it were right the actually
what is the expected value don't so you
don't assume that the fact of these two
things being in close proximity to each
other is unlikely until you know the
frequency of the one thing that you
think shouldn't have shown up there and
if it were true that there were one in
every city over I don't know two hundred
thousand in China then it's relative
proximity to a market that sells fresh
food is completely unsurprising and
warrants no discussion at all and you
know I'd love to see the goodness of fit
test the chi-square or whatever - to
know whether or not the these two things
the you know the fish market and the
virology lab being in relative proximity
to one another is unlikely compared to
other cities of comparable or larger
size I think would be the right analysis
for Wuhan but suffice it to say that the
fact that the question was even asked
and that the answer apparently without
any numbers to it came back was like oh
no actually these labs are quite
uncommon tells us okay well at least
they passed that first step of this is
this seems to be unlikely yeah seems to
be unlikely at an extraordinary level
and I mean I must say if I can just
remind people of the story we discovered
that there was some pandemic about to
unfold when we emerged from the Amazon
in late January late January we were in
Ecuador and there was one case thought
to be in Ecuador and so it came across
our local twitter feeds and at that
point I looked at it and I was not happy
to discover that the bat had been
implicated as a bat biologist I always
feel you know it's kind of a loss when
more is added to the reasons to fear
bats and anyway but I looked at it and
it looked pretty plausible that this had
come through the fish market through the
sale of bats and when I tweeted that
this looked reasonable to me I got back
in a media
influx of people showing me a Chinese
job advertisement for a virology lab in
Wuhan looking to study coronaviruses now
of course I don't speak Bandar and I
couldn't evaluate whether what I was
seeing was actually even a real document
much less what it said but I suddenly
knew that there were things about this
story I didn't understand because it is
an amazing coincidence for there to be a
virology lab studying coronaviruses in
Wuhan for the epidemic to have started
there and for them to have been
advertising for people to study these
exact kinds of questions so I backed
immediately off of that and I have to
say in the period of time since then it
has not gotten more likely that it was
the fish market it the more you chased
down the various possibilities the less
likely it looks so I was going to offer
one suggestion going forward and I've
done it myself and I would suggest
everybody who is interested in these
questions do it also which is you make a
kind of flute flowchart of the various
different possibilities in play
unfortunately we've been given an
artificial it's either natural and it
came from a bat with no lab involvement
or somebody designed this virus you know
in some extreme form and there's lots of
intermediate possibilities but I would
suggest you map them all out so that
they're all on a piece of paper and then
you put percentages based on what you
know about the likelihood that it came
this way that way and you fill the thing
out as much as possible and then you put
a date on it so that you know as of this
date this is where I understood the
likelihoods to be and you don't stick to
it you know again I'm still rooting for
the natural came from nature without the
involvement of a lab hypothesis I just
don't think it's very likely to be true
so do you have this flow chart that you
made it that you wanted Zack to show or
or no we could do that and I just I want
people to understand I don't want to
live or die by whether or not this flow
chart generated yesterday and today is
accurate again I'm rooting for it to be
wrong and I'm just I haven't seen it yet
so this could this could be interesting
let's see it together if if you can show
that ours
so I can see it might have a copy of it
here well actually if dad has a copy
that's Zach our producer and our son
so wait zach is our son which makes us
his British true right yeah I'm pretty
sure that's our cursive for sure yes
okay oh great oh except we can't really
read it but you have a cop goodness that
is terrible can you fix that at all Zach
no well is that supposed to be a PDF all
right well I guess we can't really show
you that in any sort of decent form okay
let's let's take it down then and and
come back to it what do we have a better
image maybe next time all right so let's
just say you all saw what the image
exactly what the image looks like
roughly the bubbles contain various
possibilities and the little percentages
in between are an estimate of the
likelihood that it went one way or
another and the total should be about a
hundred percent because it should be
somewhere on the flow chart is the
actual path it took to humanity you want
to switch gears and talk a little bit
about excess deaths sure yeah yeah let's
talk about excess dust this is a this is
a concept that you've raised a few times
or we have raised a few times I guess
let me let me set it up for a minute
before you before you talk a little bit
about it by saying that much has been
made of late by those who are advocating
for an end to lock downs and a return to
normal return to normal in quotes that
we don't have an accurate count ounce of
deaths or of underlying infection rates
which has been one of my drumbeats that
without without widespread testing we
don't know underlying infection rates
and therefore we do not know we can't
possibly have an accurate case fatality
rate or infection fatality rate but some
people more likely to be on the right
than the left at the moment
unfortunately and by unfortunately by
which I mean unfortunately it's
polarized politically this way some
people who believe or want us to believe
that the threat of this virus is being
overplayed
we'll say things use the language of you
don't die with a disease you die of a
disease and this is prompted by I think
it was dr. bricks is it because on the
coronavirus task force saying that at
the moment if you have tested positive
for Koba 19 and you die that is being
slated in the official death tolls as
you died of coma at 19 and some people
have said that's ridiculous
you don't die with you die of and and
you know if if if that critique is true
it would skew the death toll higher
towards coma 19 alright but this is
dealt with I think really well by the
concept of excess deaths so you want to
speak to that sure so you can imagine
that there's some sort of fluctuation in
the amount of death that you will see at
different times of year winter is harder
on people you'll have more people dying
during the winter than when times are
easy something like that but by
comparing one year to the next so you
take a given week you know first week in
January let's say and you compare how
many people died in this municipality
this year versus next year or last year
you see what the change is over time and
you'll get some sort of noise you know
some years you have a few more deaths
some years you'll have a few less but in
general you'll have some sort of
expected level of death and then you
have some major event like the kovat 19
pandemic and you can compare in the Cova
19 pandemic you have this many people
died in the given week in question
compared to what normal would look like
and you say well we've got you know 270
extra deaths that are not expected
mm-hmm
which of course doesn't mean it doesn't
there are two things it doesn't mean one
it doesn't mean those people even had
Kovac 19 some of them may have died from
consequences of kovat 19 that were not
direct like they didn't go to the doctor
when they had signs of a stroke and that
killed them so it may be a consequence
of kovat 19 but not a calm
sequence of not a pathological
consequence of it in the individual
right so in any case I had a second
category I was looking for I don't think
you said it yet yeah what was it I don't
remember I want to be in a second but
but by and large the important thing is
oh there's also you know noise you could
have s reasons that people would there
be there could be other on unknown
reasons that you would have excess
deaths in a year that would tend to be
attributed to covet 19 because kovat 19
was the big factor everybody was
thinking about but by and large that
ought to be a small factor either that
or you ought to see the yearly variation
is actually large in which case your
goal would be large meaning you weren't
very confident of the the usual baseline
mm-hmm
but anyway excess des is a good way of
capturing that which is hard to parse
specifically how many people are dying
as a result of cope at 19 we can
estimate it maybe better with excess des
than we do with any other measure yeah
exactly and I wanted to add just one
thing to this which is that the concept
of excess deaths the statistic of excess
deaths how many people died in this
place at this time compared to the
deaths per capita at this place exactly
a year ago to control for seasonality
and to care to compare to control for
geography then this will find
potentially other syndromes that we
meaning epidemiologists virologists
medical health professionals are not yet
attributing to coronavirus so Zach if
you would put this up there is a strange
new terrifying inflammatory condition in
children pediatric cases which is not
tending to kill children but it is
tending to leave them extremely sick and
with who knows what level of long term
consequences so in this particular case
there are there are strong suggestions
that that this pediatric inflammatory
condition is indeed caused by
coronavirus and so you've got people
looking into whether or not these
children who have this many of them
either test positive now or test
positive for antibodies suggesting
they've been exposed to the corona virus
in the past that that itself is a little
alarming and it's in keeping with other
things that we know about the
progression of this disease and many
people wherein you get sick those people
who aren't asymptomatic get sick and
seem to be getting better and then
plummet and then have some strong
respiratory problem that causes causes
them to in some cases die in some cases
require ICU so the fact that this is you
can take that town please the fact that
this is found in children who have
antibodies to SARS Cove - but don't
currently test positive again suggests
that a there may be longer term
consequence that the progression of this
disease may be maybe have a much longer
arc than people are imagining that it's
not like you get better and you're done
but also this you know if children were
actually dying from this which it looks
you know thankfully like children aren't
actually dying but they're getting very
sick and we didn't yet attribute to this
to possible coronavirus effects that
would still show up under excess deaths
and this may well suggest that there are
other things like for instance strokes
in otherwise healthy relatively young
people people in their 30s and 40s who
are suffering home strokes and very much
higher levels right now well is there
something else that's going on that's
explanatory or is that somehow linked to
SARS Cove - either way
it's a scary answer and it'll show up in
the excess deaths count in a way that
other metrics don't have a way of
revealing yeah and it is a good it's a
good integrative measure that to the
extent that we're trying to figure out
policy wives what to do if we can go
back to the disk
we were having at the beginning it's
really perhaps the key metric for
actually capturing the hazard at least
as far as it manifests in deaths and as
you allude to that is not the only
frightening thing here it's not that if
you get better you're better the fact
that large numbers are a large fraction
of people even who've been asymptomatic
have visible pathology on their x-rays
after they've recovered I suggest that
this may indeed be a very dangerous life
shortening condition even for the lucky
ones who show no symptoms yep
well there's a number of other things we
could talk about here you have any
preference between timing mmm more
virulent strains or talking about
relative risks
well more virulent strains is certainly
worth talking about okay and maybe we
should mention Johns Hopkins statistics
which frankly I find so shocking that I
feel there might be something wrong with
them I don't have them up here maybe
well maybe we could mention those in the
Q&A because I don't use something to be
my phone so I don't have them on the
computer sorry about that um so let's
say you want to talk about a deuce train
with higher virulence so let's see this
is LA Times reports a new study I
haven't actually looked at this much
which is not pulling up because Internet
is okay I'm not sure what to say about
this because we don't have anything on
the screen here yes there's nothing on
the screen there well let's see there's
some there's some evidence that out of
Los Alamos some researchers at Los
Alamos that there are as we've talked
about before a new small Teeple strains
and that some of the strains that seemed
at least one of the strains that seems
to have traveled from Europe to the
eastern seaboard in the US
and whenever that might have been
estimates very is a more virulent strain
than the first one that was emerging in
Wuhan in December November and December
of 2019 and this is again an idea that
has been wildly dismissed by some uh
there aren't multiple strains and you
know this this raises the question of
what what makes it a multiple what makes
it a different strain clearly the thing
is mutating it would because it's it's
made of RNA it's going to mutate and at
what point hasn't mutated sufficiently
that someone has decided to call it a
different strain and you know we we're
more familiar with this over in
non-viral organism space when we're
talking about often in vertebrates at
what point do you call it a different
species well it's a judgement call and
the experts within that clade of
organisms get to decide when we call out
of different spaces and when we don't
and sometimes they reverse their
decision and they say actually we think
actually these these two things that we
were calling different species are one
or more often vice versa so with regard
to a quickly evolving newly emerged
virus that the world has never seen
before
at what point is is it changed enough
from its original that we're calling a
different strain at some level I don't
even find the question very interesting
but you know that what do we call it
yeah
but the hasn't mutated and are some of
the lineages from the original one more
virulent than others they would have to
be well let's do have to be very instant
virulence let's try to correct this so
people understand what's really taking
place and why this why the question
turns out not to be a good one
right yeah it's very important one the
question of how many strains how many
strains are they here's the thing let's
say you've got kovat 19 or you've got
SARS co2 and our suffering from Koba 19
you undoubtedly have multiple strains in
you right there will have been mutations
that will cause differences most of
those differences won't change anything
about the way it functions so we'll
never notice that there are differences
and most of those changes will die with
the end of the infection that you
so some new strain comes into existence
in some individual and then that person
gets better and there are no live
viruses left and that strain came into
existence and went extinct without
anybody recognizing it that's happening
I would that in every single patient hmm
I mean they're just simply boy am I
gonna get this number wrong but I would
guess there are hundreds of billions of
copies of the virus in every sick person
who has had the disease long enough for
it to get to all the tissues it's gonna
get to that number could be trillions
could be yeah or does a bank but let's
just say let's be conservative at let's
say it's many millions okay chances that
all of them are identical and have not
had a mutation are pretty low given the
way mutation occurs and the chances that
the one that has the mutation escapes to
the next person is pretty low given that
most of them will be identical or near
identical copies from the original
occasionally a mutation will jump to
somebody new but very often that
mutation won't change anything about the
functionality so we won't notice it and
then it'll go extinct in the next person
but every so often the virus will
accidentally innovate something that
makes it more effective than its
ancestor when that happens the chances
that it does persist to get into the
next person goes up which doesn't mean
it will make it but it does mean that
chances are greater yeah so at some
point one of these lucky changes will
make a leap and when it makes a leap the
lucky change will make a second leap and
as it fans out into more and more
individuals the chances that that new
slightly better version will take hold
and be in an effective new patient zero
right a new patient zero for that new
strain that then fans out to a bunch of
people is fairly large can I do another
potentially obnoxious semantic thing and
center you use the term better which
will be grabbed on to by the critics to
suggest that you think it's better
and the virus becomes what more
virulence for awful to humanity what
does what does better mean to me right
it means I'm just I'm trying to play
your trail here yeah I think I think
it's useful so hey you should know
personality defect I very much dislike
this virus but it's not right don't
admire the beauty of its design I do I'm
not rooting for it yeah but you don't
want the virus lovers out there getting
on your case I am perfectly capable of
really disliking mosquitoes and finding
them fascinating and an admirable feat
of inadvertent design but in any case
better means more capable of making it
farther into the future I'm rooting
against the making in the future but
when they do it's better from their
perspective and what it is trying to do
which is the opposite of what we want it
to do yeah so when it gets better we
lose more you want out to get there we
want to stop it's better strains it's
better lineages in their tracks
yes except that it is possible that it I
don't think we're anywhere near this but
it's possible it could go benign and do
things that are better for it and less
costly to us in which case we might root
for that but but in any case you've got
a virus trying to lodge itself into the
future and mutation is the recipe for
discovery or it is the first ingredient
in the recipe for discovery of new
mechanisms and I must say that this all
echoes back to the question of where
this thing came from and why a rational
person would conclude one thing or
another one of the salient facts about
this virus is that several versions of
it showed up in several early patients
in wuhan who all apparently had the same
sequence suggesting that this was not
the result of experimentation on the
part of the virus but that it was good
to go with respect to moving from one
person to the next so the question of
new strains is tied up in the question
of
how likely is this virus to acquire a
mutation that makes it less simple for
us to control mm-hmm and so the new
strain thing is very dangerous and I
should also say that this is tied up in
a question that you and I began to
grapple with this week which is social
distancing is actually a fractal problem
yes that there is a hazard when two
people meet in close enough proximity to
transmit this virus and then there is an
even greater hazard the farther you
travel because a person who travels over
a hundred miles a thousand miles
whatever it might be is in danger of
taking a strain that was resident in one
part of the country or the world and
transmitting it to a new part of the
world and you know you could have a
strain that is not well adapted to cold
climates and you could end up
transmitting it to a warm climate from a
cold climate where it would have had a
hard time and you transmit it to
someplace where we'll have an easy time
and so the chances of us stamping out
sardis Cove - are even lower because
we've now given it a foothold somewhere
that it's better adapted so these
questions really have to be thought
about and I guess maybe the overarching
plea would be somehow we need to get a
group of people who is smart enough who
is educated with the right sort of
background so that they can understand
these and completely free of corrupting
influences and perverse incentives so
that we can have a broad ranging
discussion of the right response to make
the likelihood of this thing remaining
pathological and permanent in the human
population as low as possible and I
don't think that discussion is taking
place everywhere because anywhere
because the degree to which those who
are in a position to understand what's
going on are also in a compromised
position with respect to what they can
say and what is in their interest to say
is extreme so let's um let's segue from
that excellent population level analysis
to just a little bit of individual level
analysis which is to say what you know
what can you do individually with just
two to keep yourself safe to make
yourself less likely of contracting this
thing which is a place that we started
or ended our very first live stream with
and I want to just show show a chart not
yet
Zach show a chart that was produced by
an MD PhD if someone who's both medical
doctor and PhD and I think it's
microbiology which just in which he puts
numbers that he's made up to the
likelihood of contracting Co but 19
under a number of circumstances so it's
a little bit like the flow chart you
know it's he's trying to estimate
different things but he's he's done an
exercise a little bit like the one that
you suggested with regard to hypotheses
right so I think this is something that
people who aren't trained in science
don't necessarily think of scientists
doing but I think that actually all the
best scientists and scientists science
minded people actually do is try to
imagine what their certainty of certain
things is and also put numbers to how
likely hypothesis or motive transmission
or something is so that they can make
decisions as opposed to just receiving
don't wear masks from the US Surgeon
General the end of February and taking
that as the God's honest truth so you
can put this up now Zac here's this MD
PhD is through estimates of what your
risk is doing different things where the
higher the relative score the the
greater the risk where he has doing a
procedure on an ICU patient in which
their intubated and their suction their
CPR it's really really high risk to you
the people in that room because the
patient if they're infected is going to
be just spewing viral particles with all
of these all of these ways similarly
working in a shift in an ER ICU full of
code patients is very risky drop down to
the bottom of the breathing exposures
walking in a big city trying to stay six
feet away and he doesn't talk about
masks here but he has separately that's
pretty low risk actually right living in
your house for a day for adults just
doing the basics you haven't had any
guests really low risk walking in a
suburban yard or street with no people
in sight he has that at zero and again
these are numbers that he's made up but
he these are these are informed guesses
and this feels like the kind of analysis
that we are not seeing nearly enough of
right and furthermore he does he does a
similar thing with fewer lines for touch
exposures and this is basically based on
so you know opening a door frequently
that's been used by other people yeah
your risk is a lot higher then if you
open a door that's been that's been
touched by a couple of people or even if
you hug or shake hands with a couple of
people that's riskier than touching a
door handle that's been touched by a lot
of people but door handles are less
risky than hugging but the more people
who have touched that door handle or
that pin pad
the higher your risk is so there's a we
heard early in this crisis a lot about
the risk of exponential growth of
infections and the flip side of that is
exponential decay of viral particles and
I know that we've talked about this a
few times on past live streams but
exponential decay of viral particles
means in short that even if someone who
was actively shedding viral particles
who was currently sick and is actively
shedding viral particles delivered a
package to your door and we know that
viral particles can live in the theory
on cardboard for up to 48 hours the
chance that any of those actually shed
out the cardboard is low but it's much
more likely that you will end up with a
viral particle that is active that
transfers to your skin within five
minutes of that cardboard being touched
by a person who's actively sick than an
hour or two hours or six hours or 24
hours such that yes it is theoretically
possible that a viral particle could be
detected
48 hours later but the chances of you
getting sick from that are far far far
lower than 24 hours later and they are
far far far lower than 6 hours and 12
hours later six hours later basically
the farther out you go you have this
exponential decay over time just like we
were predicting and we seem to have seen
in a lot of cases exponential growth of
sickness over time so this is it perfect
this connects what we started these
livestreams
discussing primarily which was how does
a an informed person facing all of the
uncertainties of this disease navigate
in the world and minimize their risks so
that it is tolerably low and what we
find is that many of our intuitions were
actually right masks help
turns out they may help more if you're
sick from transmitting it to other
people which raises a question of game
theory but nonetheless it appears that
when both parties are wearing them it's
the best situation and being outside
appears to be safe if not protective
there's an opportunity cost of being
indoors things being delivered to you
create some risk but it's manageable by
virtue of how you deal with the
packaging if you take the thing out of
the outer package so that you're dealing
with something that probably hasn't been
touched by a human in 48 hours you're
probably pretty close to zero if you
then wash your hands so that anything
you touched couldn't get into you the
fact that dosage appears to be related
MEMS that low dosages on a package that
comes to you are probably pretty safe to
begin with so anyway I think this is
good and what I'm hoping actually that
people get out of this is that there is
a way of navigating these questions
without certainty that does have a
positive effect on your behavior and its
likelihood of protecting you okay and
maybe the place where are we time we're
over an hour
we're over an hour maybe the place to to
close this out is to mention these
numbers I remember too
of them vividly and again I'm not saying
these numbers are accurate but I'm
saying that their source is high-quality
and they stopped me in my tracks when I
read them the first one was this is a
Johns Hopkins researcher I believe has
written a short letter objecting to some
of the characterizations of how bad the
pandemic is is that right right and I
think this plays into the question of
you know it's a time to go back to
normally etc and the two statistics I
recall were that kovat 19 is now the
leading cause of death in the United
States I find that very surprising and
you know the naysayers will say that
lots of things are being attributed to
kovat 19 that that shouldn't be but but
at the very least kovat 19 is killing a
huge number of people
if the metrics that are being used
suggest that it is killing more people
than any other cause of death it is
killing guard 'less of whether or not
that number is flawed it is killing them
with the lockpick yes so the concern is
not only do we have an evolutionary
hazard if we would lift a lockdown where
the virus gets more room to discover new
ways of infecting people and jumping
from one place to another but we have
just the simple virus as it exists doing
more of what it does and killing more
people the other statistic was that
something like 1 in 500 New Yorkers and
I think this is New York City that we're
talking about but one in 500 New Yorkers
has died from this yeah just 0.2% and
that's not 8.2% case fatality rate that
is a point two percent mortality rate in
the population so if a hundred percent
of New Yorkers have been exposed which
no one thinks they have then that means
ok 0.2 percent of people who have this
thing die that seems kind of low and
it's still not okay but there's no way
no one thinks that a hundred percent of
New Yorkers have had this thing no one
even really thinks that 50% of New
Yorkers have had it so if 2 percent of
New Yorkers have had it and point two
percent of New Yorkers have died from it
that's ten
of people who have it are dying and if
more percentage higher percentage than
that of New Yorkers I've had it which is
probably true then that fatality rate
goes down but one in 500 New Yorkers are
dead in the last few months from this
and again with the caveat around you
from versus with this disease and all
that but that is a staggering number
it's a staggering number and if we if
we've misunderstood the Johns Hopkins
report let us know what we've
misunderstood but it seemed fairly
straightforward I guess the the
conclusion of all of this I think is
let's be let's be decent about it there
is something unprecedented and
frightening about the lockdown and its
consequences the idea that we cannot
gather in large numbers is frankly it is
presumably unconstitutional on the other
hand what we are facing is so serious
that we are having to navigate with new
tools against an enemy that doesn't know
about or care about the Constitution so
I'm actually gonna push back on that
like we we need to go yeah but I don't
think it is unconstitutional and there's
a good analysis out there by someone
who's actually on the right it was a
legal scholar that I don't have today
but I don't know you're going to go
there that says no actually in times of
mass risk which is specifically Public
Health the Constitution the government
is allowed to expand its powers so long
as it restrict its restricts its powers
again once the threat has passed well
let me say this I believe that's
probably true and we do this all the
time but then the Constitution and I
believe this is right has to be treated
as a living document the right to bear
arms doesn't imply the right to have
nuclear weapons
so obviously discretion is the key to
making the document work and in this
case I think the point would be that
discretion used properly means that this
is to the extent that disappears to
challenge
constitutional provision it is warranted
which does not make all such things
warranted we've seen lots of stuff in
light of terrorism where government
overreach has been extreme and without
cause but all right so let's say we're
gonna take a break for 15 minutes we're
gonna come back with Q&A from super
check questions if did they come in Zach
yeah okay excellent and we're gonna
start though we're gonna start the Q&A
in about 15 minutes from the length that
you'll find in the description of this
livestream by addressing echoes question
from last time which was about whether
or not male genitalia size and female
brain size are linked evolutionarily and
why that might be the case so that's the
teaser that's where we'll start next
time in about 15 minutes all right we
will see you then